<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maciej Szalewicz</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Maciej Szalewicz</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    

    
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 10:20:42 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>SQLite Pitfalls</title>
      <link>/blog/2024_11_10_sqlite_pitfalls/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 10:20:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024_11_10_sqlite_pitfalls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34; &gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#intro&#34;&gt;
        #
    &lt;/a&gt;
    Intro
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SQLite is the world’s  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sqlite.org/mostdeployed.html&#34;&gt;most widely&lt;/a&gt; used database, powering the backends of countless applications. For most software, it offers a reliable solution for embedded data storage, eliminating the need to reinvent the wheel. Its broad adoption means developers benefit from a well-documented, dependable tool with a familiar SQL dialect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent interest in SQLite has surged, particularly due to its fit for two key technological trends. First, it’s a strong choice for multi-tenant architectures, where platforms like Turso leverage SQLite to give each tenant an isolated database. This setup simplifies data management while maintaining privacy and scalability​. Second, SQLite has found new applications in web-based environments with the rise of WebAssembly (WASM). By embedding SQLite databases directly into browsers, developers can provide fast, local data storage that complements server-side databases. This enables efficient offline functionality and performance gains for web apps​. For a detailed example of this use case, check out Notion’s excelent blog &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notion.so/blog/how-we-sped-up-notion-in-the-browser-with-wasm-sqlite&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on how they sped up their browser app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more people, myself included, are becoming intrigued by SQLite. However, for those transitioning from other database systems, there are a few surprising differences to discover.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
